<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true guide to glory A sermon preached at Plympton-Mary in Deuon, at the funerals of the right vvorshipfull, and ...</title>
            <author>Barlow, John, b. 1580 or 81.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04284</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1440</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114791</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850014</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850014</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15197</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04284)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15197)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 824:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true guide to glory A sermon preached at Plympton-Mary in Deuon, at the funerals of the right vvorshipfull, and ...</title>
                  <author>Barlow, John, b. 1580 or 81.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 51, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Snodham, for Nathaniel Newberry, and are to be sold at his shop vnder Saint Peters Church in Cornehill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: I. B. [i.e. John Barlow].</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The true guide vnto glory.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; title page mutilated with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15197:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15197:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TRVE GVIDE To <hi>GLORY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED at Plympton Mary in <hi>Deuon,</hi> at the Funerals of the Right VVorſhipfull, and truely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the LADY <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>10.</hi>
                  </bibl> When <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>11.</hi>
                  </bibl> Then ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> thee, and vnderſtanding ſhall keepe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by THOMAS SNODHAM, for <hi>Nathaniel Newberrie,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop vnder Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Church in <hi>Cornehill.</hi> 1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15197:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15197:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT <hi>WORSHIPFVLL,</hi> and his approued good friends; <hi>Sir</hi> WILLIAM STRODE <hi>of Nowingham</hi> in <hi>Deuon,</hi> Knight, with his SONNES and DAVGHTERS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the watchman (Right Worſhipfull) ſaid to <hi>Dauid,</hi> The running of the foremoſt is like the running of <hi>Ahi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maaz;</hi> then the King ſaid, He is a good man, and commeth with good tidings. Now I would it could at this time be truely teſtified of me, in both particulars: but it may not; it cannot. For I am like to him that addeth fewel to the flame; rubbeth a greene wound; or that preſents, before the eye, ſome fearefull, and to-be forgotten obiect. The tidings I bring, are like the Amalekites to <hi>Dauid; Ioſephs</hi> brethren to <hi>Iacob;</hi> or <hi>Ionah</hi> his Sermon to the Niniuites: Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, beare with me, for I cannot helpe it: It's God that did it; and good vſe may be made of it.</p>
            <p>Wee muſt all fall in the wilderneſſe of this</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:15197:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt</hi> was not amiſſe compared to a mourner: for his attire was hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; his foode locuſts and wilde hony; and his Doctrine, to fleſh and blood, ſounded harſhly: So may all my Sonnes, and that not vnfitly, be ſtiled the ſubiects of ſorrow; for the weedes, wherein they be wrapped, are blacke; their faces, eyes, cheekes repreſent death, iudgement, the graue; and their tongues tell of heauy and terrible tidings. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, doe not thou too raſhly condemne their father; for their mother, Time, was womanfull of great infirmities; in whoſe wombe they were conceiued; ſo that he gaue them not all, but part of their being. Are not theſe the dayes of danger, times of perill, ſo long agone fore-told, propheſied? Shall wee then expect iſſue of Peace, or ſonnes of Laughter? Nay rather looke for a ſorrowfull ſeede and cruell Poſterity.</p>
            <p>Yet this I would haue thee to vnderſtand, that (though their heads be hanging, their lookes lowring, and this Motto imprinted in their Brow, <hi>Woe to the wicked inhabitants of the Earth:</hi>) thou haſt no iuſt cauſe to ſhut thy doores, veile thine eyes, or to deny them a friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entertainement; for they, in many things, doe reſemble
<pb facs="tcp:15197:3"/> thy ſelfe, beare the ingrauen image of thy perſon, and truely declare, what, before long, ſhall certainely befall thee. They ſpeake rudely, bluntly, yet truely; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in cenſure them not ouer-ſuddenly: for it's their fathers language; of him they haue learned it; ſo that it's become their naturall Dialect: And he taught them all, and firſt of all, this impartiall leſſon; <hi>That, in their progreſſe and ſpeech, they ſhould value all men alike, of what cloath ſoeuer their coates be cut on, vntill a New birth had put a difference.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I eaſily conceiue the murmurings of many, mumbling: What? is not the world full of ſuch children? I haue often ſeene, that ſuch as haue no ſeede of their owne, ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome affect the poſterity of another: Or, peraduenture, ſome (who are paſt begetting any) may obiect or cauell; Why, this is not the ſame, I was preſent at his birth. My good friend, know (if it were ſo) that a better coate changeth not the ſubiect; neither doth a new patch alter the forme of an old garment; for then <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in his Princely Robes, had beene another man, and <hi>Zebede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> his old nets had become new by mending. Shall we conclude, that when an Hebraiſme, by our Lord an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Diſciples, is turned into a Graeciſme, that the Scripture is wreſted or altered? But theſe perſons are like the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren wombe, in a double reſpect; they are vnfruitfull, and yet with foaming out their owne ſhame, and ſpetting innocent infants in the face, they be neuer ſatisfied. Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit his Father, ſuſpect thy owne cenſure: for when thou ſaweſt him firſt, he was running; and thine eye might eaſily deceiue thee: now he is ſitting, thou maiſt take a more certaine view of him, and ſee him as he is.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15197:4"/>
            <p>He that will iudge wine for colour, in the powring; or mens ſuites on their backes, running; may eaſily deeme amiſſe in his forward cenſuring. But handle the one, and ſee the other in a glaſſe ſetled, ſo ſhalt thou not be at all deluded: In like manner, words vttered are in moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the Eare cannot ſo well receiue them, as being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed in papers, the Eye will apprehend them: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, be ſwift to heare, ſlow to ſpeake; and then iudge righteous iudgement.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my ſtudy in</hi> Ply<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mouth.</dateline>
               <signed>Thy Chriſtian friend, I. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15197:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE TRVE GVIDE VNTO GLORY.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 73.24.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Thou wilt guide me by thy counſell; and afterward receiue me to glory.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Oncerning this Pſalme, two things may be conſidered: Firſt, the Author of it; Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Subiect of it. <hi>Aſaph,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chro. 29.30.</note> ſome thinke, Penned it; for it is ſtiled <hi>A Pſalme of Aſaph:</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, he writ Pſalmes as well as <hi>Dauid:</hi> alſo,<note place="margin">1 Chro. 25.2.</note> hee and his Sonnes were ſingers in <hi>Iſrael:</hi> But whether he, <hi>Dauid,</hi> or <hi>Moſes</hi> made it, the matter is not much, ſeeing it is moſt certaine, <hi>hee was carried and directed by the Spirit of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. <hi>vlt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that penn'd it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As touching the ſubiect matter of it, if we looke into it, we ſhall finde a plaine deſcription of a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and godly man; the very mappe of both in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15197:5"/> liuely colours declared, and that for the preſent and future time. The vngodly is ſet forth. Firſt, by his <hi>Adiuncts,</hi> which are ſixe. 1. In his title <hi>foole.</hi> 2. his Strength. 3. his Riches. 4. his Succeſſe. 5. he is not corrected as others. 6. laſtly. Hee dieth in peace; <hi>for there is no bands in his death.</hi> Secondly, he is deſcri ed by his Acts, or Effects; which are likewiſe ſixe. 1. he declareth his Pride. 2. he is vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent. 3. hee Oppreſſeth. 4 hee Corrupteth, either himſelfe or others. 5. he vſeth bad Language, for <hi>his tongue walketh.</hi> 6. and laſt of all, he accuſeth God of ignorance; <hi>Is there knowledge in the moſt High?</hi> Yet you haue not heard the worſt of him: for foure accidents remaine behinde. One, his preſent eſtate is tickle; <hi>for hee ſtandeth vpon a ſlippery foundation:</hi> another, he dieth Suddenly: a third, he muſt come to Iudgement; and in concluſion, <hi>then his image ſhall be deſpiſed.</hi> And thus haue you an end of him: From all which, by the way, we may obſerue diuers inſtructions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That, wicked men are fooles: yet, the more wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, the more fooliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That, the ſtrongeſt bodies poſſeſſe not the ſoundeſt mindes:</hi> Theſe two doe not alwayes lodge toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.<note place="margin">3 Iohn 2.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn,</hi> writing to his friend <hi>Gaius,</hi> wiſheth that <hi>he might proſper and fare, as his ſoule fared:</hi> But hee that would ſend an Epiſtle to many of our Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants, if he did well, ſhould in his ſalutations deſire, that <hi>They might fare in ſoule as their bodies fare; for, they are luſty and ſtrong,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 22.23.</note> 
               <hi>their breaſts full of milke, and their bones runne full of marrow;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 5.28.</note> 
               <hi>they are waxen fat and ſhining.</hi> But where <hi>grace</hi> entreth, like a pinching
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15197:5"/> froſt, it maketh the fleſh wither and fall, freezeth the very marrow, and congealeth the fatneſſe; ſo that the body often is weake and pineth away.<note place="margin">Pſal. 39.11.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That much goods and Grace are not inſeparable companions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe two meete not, as the Sunne and Moone runne their courſe night and day, in one and the ſame ſubiect. Therefore ſaith our Lord,<note place="margin">Matth. 19.23.</note> 
               <hi>How hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhall a rich man enter into the kingdome of heauen, and be ſaued?</hi> Sometimes we grant they may, but ſeldome. It is ſaid that <hi>Naaman the Syrian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>was a mighty man, and valiant, but a Leper:</hi> great for riches, (peraduenture) valiant for body; ſo that it may proue this (at the leaſt the former) Doctrine.</p>
            <p>But what rich or ſtrong man amongſt vs beleeues this report?</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>That, wicked perſons often proſper. Their Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke gendreth and faileth not:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 21.8 9. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Their Cow calueth and caſteth not her Calfe. They ſend foorth their children like ſheepe; and their Sonnes daunce: Their Seede is eſtabliſhed, and they grow vp in wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>That not to be afflicted, is a marke of the wicked. They haue no changes, therefore they feare not God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 55.19.</note> whereas the godly are chaſtened <hi>euery morning; elſe bastards, not ſonnes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.8.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>That, peace in death is no ſure ſigne of a better life.</hi> They that liue like Lyons, and dye like Lambs, may not haue their <hi>names writ in the Lambes Booke of life.</hi> But if a good life be the Antecedent, this no bad, but a deſireable conſequent; this croſſeth the iudgement of the common people: Oh ſay ſome, how quietly he dyed? But I ſay; how well
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15197:6"/> hath hee liued? Let vs then iudge men by their liues, not by their deaths; leſt we acquit the guilty, and condemne the innocent: <hi>For all outward things come alike to all men; iuſt, or vniuſt: This is one of thoſe euils,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.1.2.3.</note> 
               <hi>that the wiſe man ſaw, vnder the Sunne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, from their Effects or Actions, might ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things be obſerued; as,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That, <hi>when wicked men haue moſt, then they ſinne moſt.</hi> Hence it is, that ſome hauing much money, turne biting Vſurers, and deuoure by oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>The bountifulneſſe of God</hi> towards them, doth not (though indeede <hi>it ought) leade them to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2.4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And from the foure following accidents, we note a foure-fold inſtruction.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that <hi>notwithſtanding the wicked be rich and ſtrong, yet they ſtand vpon a ſandy foundation. They are ſet on ſlippery places;</hi> either vpon the Ice, on the which if they ſlippe, or it breake, they be drowned, ſpoyled: or vpon a Quag-mire, that is growne ouer with a thin skinne, through which, if they ſhrinke, they ſticke faſt, and are all be-mudded.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that <hi>wicked men ſhall dye certainly, and ſuddenly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 12.2.</note> 
               <hi>in a moment:</hi> the Text ſaith; <hi>They ſpend their dayes in pleaſure, and ſuddenly goe downe to the graue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, that <hi>prophane perſons ſhall riſe, and come to iudgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And laſtly, that <hi>at the day of iudgement they ſhall haue their full torment:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 12.1.</note> For, <hi>they ſhall riſe to ſhame and contempt eternall.</hi> And thus we leaue them, where God ſhall leaue them, wiſhing their harmes may
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15197:6"/> make vs to beware: And ſo proceede we to the godly perſon, of whom wee haue many things to ſay; but becauſe time will not permit vs, we will omit them, onely reducing them to theſe heads,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>A Conflict,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>The Iſſue of it.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> In this Combat, note
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Who they be that quarrell.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>The cauſes of it.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>It is the Fleſh and Spirit, Faith and Infidelity that ſtriue; theſe twins are in euery regenerate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, man or woman. Sinne muſt not be counted as a meere priuation, or nothing; but we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue of it <hi>as a ſtrong man, or corroborated habit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.24. &amp;c.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The ground of the quarrell groweth either from the fell oppoſition, that is betwixt them; for theſe are <hi>contrary one to the other:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.17.</note> or the diuers conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the wicked and the godly. When the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane man proſpereth, and the righteous are in aduerſity, it worketh ſtrangely, euen in the moſt ſincere hearted: Therefore the wicked are coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted bleſſed; For, <hi>they that worke wickedneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>they are ſet vp, and ſuch as tempt God, they are deliuered.</hi> From this conſideration, this good mans ſteps had almoſt ſlipt, and he embraced the world; yet he hauing recourſe to the word of God, ſaw his owne folly, and their miſerable end; ſo that though the combat for a time was fierce, and the iſſue thereof doubtfull, notwithſtanding Faith preuaileth at the length, and winnes the field, triumphing with this confeſſion; <hi>Lord, thou wilt guide me, &amp;c.</hi> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee come to the words, let vs obſerue ſome things by the way. And here we may ſee, that</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:15197:7"/>1. <hi>The proſperity of the wicked fretteth the godly.</hi> There is a ſecret enmity betweene the ſeede of the Woman, and the Serpents; Alſo that,</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>In the time of temptation, the fleſh will play its part.</hi> Furthermore, that</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>He that would ſee the preſent and future condition of good and bad, muſt haue recourſe to Gods word;</hi> not flocke to the Stage or prophane Hiſtory, for they may deceiue; this Booke cannot.</p>
            <p>And ſo we come to the words in hand, the which haue a double reading at the leaſt: Some reade them prayer-wiſe; <hi>Lord guide me, &amp;c.</hi> But I rather chooſe to reade them as a Confeſſion, being a ſpeech of great reioycing, and a declaration of the fruit of his faith, that followed this great and terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble combat.</p>
            <p>In the which we may obſerue a double propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and in either of them, two principall things comprehended. In the antecedent part, this good man ſaith; Firſt, that <hi>the Lord will guide him.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, he acknowledgeth wherewith, <hi>viz. by his counſell.</hi> In the conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>quent propoſition, hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſeth, that <hi>he will alſo glorifie him;</hi> and telleth the time when, or order how; <hi>after he had guided him by his counſell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you ſee the parts of it. Now we come to ſhew you the meaning or ſenſe of the words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou,]</hi> that is, GOD; Father, Sonne, and holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t; for all three conſent in euery action done to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the creature: what one doth, all doe, medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately or immediately, yet in a diuers manner: <hi>God</hi> the Father is ſaid to <hi>guide,</hi> by the word; <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15197:7"/> his example, and the <hi>Spirit,</hi> by immediate moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and irradiations iniected vpon mans vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; yet with one ioynt conſent, all tend to one and the ſame thing. There be Relatiue proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in the <hi>Deity,</hi> that are peculiar to the diſtinct per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. As the Father to beget, the Sonne to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, and the Spirit to proceede: but theſe wee ſpeake of are internall, not externall, actions vpon the creature.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shalt,</hi> or <hi>wilt.]</hi> This word containeth in it, the faith and confidence of the perſon; how that hee did depend vpon God, and aſſure himſelfe, that he would be his guide for future time, as well as for the preſent ſeaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Guide.]</hi> This word ſeemes to be borrowed from a Traueller, and ſo all the Text is metaphorically ſet downe, or by way of ſimilitude; the ſenſe is, that the Lord would direct, quietly and ſecurely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, leade and gouerne him, in theſe his ſpirituall trauels.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mee.]</hi> That is, <hi>Aſaph, Dauid, Moſes,</hi> or ſome ſuch Seer, or faithfull perſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By thy counſell.]</hi> In Scripture counſell hath many acceptions, which wee omit; for in this place is meant, the <hi>Lords counſell:</hi> And it is two-fold; <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret,</hi> or <hi>reuealed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 15 8.</note> 
               <hi>Who hath knowne the ſecret</hi> (viz. <hi>counſell) of God?</hi> that is, what things hee purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with himſelfe, to bring to paſſe from all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> How can <hi>counſell</hi> be aſcribed vnto <hi>God?</hi> for hee ſeeth at the firſt, with one act, what is beſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſponſ. </seg>1</label> It's true, God doth ſo; yet, as we diſcerne, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15197:8"/> whileſt wee behold things, how ſucceſſiuely they come to paſſe, and are effected by ſecondary cauſes, we acknowledge it to be in him; and ſo attribute counſell vnto him.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſponſ. </seg>2</label> Againe, becauſe the Lord doth all things in iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and with deliberation;<note place="margin">Gen. 1.26. Iob 12.13.</note> (I ſpeake after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men) not raſhly or ignorantly.</p>
            <p>Now for the Reueiled <hi>counſell of God,</hi> the which is here eſpecially meant; that may be double alſo: being conſidered, in his workes, or in his word. In his workes;<note place="margin">Iſai 46.10. Prou. 19.21.</note> and that of Creation, Prouidence: For in both doth the <hi>counſell of the moſt High</hi> declare it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>But I vnderſtand, principally in this place, to be meant <hi>the word and reueiled will of God, both Law and Goſpell;</hi> the one was declared, (b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing writ in <hi>Adams</hi> heart) at the Creation; the other part af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mans fall, in the meanes of his recouery and <hi>Redemption;</hi> when indeede was manifeſted the depth of his counſell; things, that before they were reueiled, paſt finding out; after, to man moſt won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull. And in Scripture, both the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Goſpell</hi> are called <hi>Gods counſell;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 23.22. Luk. 7 30.</note> and as inſtrumentall cauſes, of neceſſity to bring man to his eternall home. And thus much for the firſt propoſition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And afterward,]</hi> that is, when my change, or time of <hi>diſſolution</hi> commeth;<note place="margin">Iob 145.14.</note> which is the end of this his pilgrimage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Receiue me.]</hi> Take me into thy protection, when I ſhall depart hence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Into glory.]</hi> For the words Etymology it ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>weight grauity. Paul</hi> alludes to this, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15197:8"/> Some reade <hi>In glory,</hi> hauing reſpect to his perſon, without ſpot or wrinkle. For,<note place="margin">Reuel. 21. <hi>vlt.</hi> 1 Tim. 3. <hi>vlt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>No vncleane thing ſhall enter into the kingdome of heauen,</hi> or into <hi>glory,</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>heauen,</hi> the glorious place of the bleſſed; both may be meant. And he hath (no doubt) relation too, to the day of iudgement,<note place="margin">Phil. 3. <hi>vlt.</hi>
               </note> when <hi>the body ſhall alſo be made glorious.</hi> So that the plaine and full meaning of this parcell of Scripture is; <hi>Lord, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that when I, with the eye of fleſh and blood, viewed the proſperity of the vngodly, how that they were luſty and ſtrong, abounding in all wealth, liuing in great plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and had no bands in their death; moreouer breaking forth into enuy, malice, oppreſsion, pride, cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſpeaking, and to blaſpheme thy Name it ſelfe; and yet not plagued like other men, who did liue in awe and feare of thy Maiesty; carefull to keepe all thy commands, and to approue their hearts to thee in all their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings; I was ſore troubled, and wonderfully perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; inſomuch as I had almoſt fainted and publiquely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed, that I had and others of thy righteous ſeruants alſo, cleanſed our hearts in vaine, and in innocency waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our hands to no purpoſe: Thus brutiſh was I, and full of infidelitie: But at the laſt, hauing recourſe vnto thy word, the Rule to decide all theſe things; I then ſaw (notwithſtanding all their pompe, pleaſure and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity) that they ſtood vpon a tickle foundation; ſhall dye certainely, ſuddenly; riſe againe, and come vnto iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when they ſhall receiue their full puniſhment for their ſinne.</hi> And, <hi>I alſo am verily perſwaded that though I am naturally ſubiect to wander, and goe aſtray, yet thou wilt direct, guide, and ſafely leade me on in this my ſpirituall and perilous paſſage (thy word reuealed to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15197:9"/> me, being my refuge as heretofore, and the meanes to conduct me, next thy Maieſty) vntill my abode here in this world, ſhall be no more: And hauing done this, I am further aſſured, that my ſoule, without ſpot or wrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle, ſhall be receiued into thy heauenly kingdome, where, in peace and ſafty, it ſhall remaine, vntill that great day, when all ſhall awake out of the duſt, and then ſhall ſoule and body be revnited, changed into the glorious image of thy Sonne, and for euer remaine in the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of thy holineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now let vs proceede to ſome points of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. We hauing heard of this great conflict betwixt the new man and the old, fleſh and ſpirit, faith and infidelity; yet corruption being at the laſt ouercome and conquered: hence I gather this Doctrine; that</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>True Faith may faint, but it neuer faileth vtterly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The degree of it (probably) may be decayed, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted; the acts and effects of it (certainely) weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, decreaſed; but the eſſence of it ſhall neuer be totally or finally conſumed, deſtroyed. <hi>Iacob may wraſtle with the Archangell, his ſinew ſhrinke, thigh fall, and his ſteps be found halting; yet ſhall he be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Iſrael:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen 32.28.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe he found fauour, and preuailed with God. Sampſon,</hi> by the deceipt of dauncing <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilah,</hi> may haue his head cut, haire ſhorne, and ſtrength goe from him; notwithſtanding in tract of time, his head ſhall grow, his vigour returne, his prayer be heard,<note place="margin">Iudg 16</note> hee kill the vncircumciſed <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtims,</hi> and haue his name enrolled for euer amongſt the faithfull.<note place="margin">Heb. 11.32. Acts 7.32.</note> The preſence of God may make <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> the man of God to break out, <hi>I quake and tremble;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15197:9"/> Iſaiah, Woe is me, I am vndone; Manoah</hi> alſo,<note place="margin">Iſa. 6.5. Iudg. 13.21.</note> 
               <hi>We ſhall ſurely dye.</hi> Notwithſtanding all this, they ſhall conquere, ouercome, paſſe to their iourneyes end in peace, win the combat: for the acts of faith be but for a time ſuſpended; the eſſence is not annihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, vtterly conſumed. Valiant <hi>Gedeon</hi> may cry aloud, <hi>How can the Lord be with vs, ſeeing all theſe euils be come vpon vs? where be his miracles of old, our fathers told vs off? hath not God forſaken vs?</hi> Yet,<note place="margin">Iudg. 6.13.14.</note> ſhall he not, anone, heare a voice, <hi>Goe in thy might, for thou (thou that thus doubteſt, feareſt) ſhalt ſaue Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael?</hi> And may not iuſt <hi>Iob</hi> thinke himſelfe to be the ſubiect of Gods wrath? the very <hi>Butt</hi> of his <hi>iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice?</hi> and (in his owne feeling) finde the <hi>arrowes of the Almighty drunke with his ſpirit?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 6.4.</note> But let him ſtay a little while, the Bowe ſhall be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ent, the ſtring ſlacked, theſe peircing ſhafts ſhut vp in the Quiuer, and his end become <hi>bleſſed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 5.11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I might here make mention of <hi>Ieremiahs</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining, and accuſing the Almighty;<note place="margin">Ier. 20.7.</note> 
               <hi>Lord I am deceiued, and thou</hi> (wonder at this) <hi>haſt deceiued me; Dauid</hi> picking a quarrell with his nature,<note place="margin">Pſal. 77.7.10. &amp; 116.11.</note> conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, <hi>This is my death, and all men are lyars; Didy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> doubting; <hi>Peter</hi> curſing and ſwearing; <hi>Paul</hi> howling. <hi>Spoiled man that I am!</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.24.</note> 
               <hi>who ſhall deliuer me from the body of this death?</hi> Yet for all this, Faith ſhall winne the field, infidelity be foiled, grace con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, corruption looſe the combat: And although the Fleſh be the firſt borne, claime poſſeſſion, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a day of mourning; yet let him doe his worſt, he ſhall looſe his birth-right, ſerue the yonger: for Faith hath beene bleſſed once, &amp; it ſhall be bleſſed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15197:10"/> euer. Art thou yet in doubt? Doeſt thou demand, How can this thing be?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> Why? is not Faith <hi>the gift of God?</hi> and are not <hi>his gifts and calling without repentance?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph 2.8. Rom. 11.29. Iam. 1.5.17.</note> Shall he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile his bounty? recall his liberality? No, no, <hi>he giueth freely, and vpbraideth no mans perſon, there is no variableneſſe, or ſhadow of turning with him.</hi> Man may, through errour of iudgement, mutation of affection, or ſome forced neceſſity, withdraw and take poſſeſſion of his former fauours conferred: But <hi>God</hi> cannot erre, be moued, or brought to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty; therefore his gift of grace that is once gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 16.14.</note> is euer giuen. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> But our aduerſaries obiect, that <hi>God tooke his Spirit from Saul.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Solut. </seg>
               </label> It's true, he did ſo; but we muſt know that the gifts of the Spirit are either common, or ſauing; now of this latter kinde, this King had not any; for ſuch are peculiar to his cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen people. God for his ſinne had a purpoſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue him of his kingdome, therefore of his Spirit, by which he ſhould haue gouerned it; were the Lord purpoſed to depriue his elect of heauen, as he was <hi>Saul</hi> of the ſcepter, then we might feare Faith might faile, and be tooke from vs; but <hi>God</hi> hath a reſolution to giue <hi>his little flocke a kingdome;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e 12.32.</note> and where he intends the end, the meanes that tend to it, ſhall certainly in ſome meaſure be continued.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> Againe, hath not <hi>Chriſt</hi> long agone <hi>prayed to his Father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e 22 32. Rom. 8.34.</note> 
               <hi>that it might not faile? And is he not now at the right hand of God, to make interceſsion for the Saints?</hi> ſhall he not preuaile? will his heauenly Father de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny him any thing?<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.8.</note> Why, this were to deny him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, to make <hi>Chriſt</hi> a lyar, ſeeing wee haue his
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15197:10"/> owne teſtimony, <hi>That he is heard at all times,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 11.42.</note> 
               <hi>in all things.</hi> Let Sathan therefore winnow the godly, as in a ſieue, tempt, plot, vſe his moſt profound depths, and raiſe vp his moſt boiſterous windes; yet his fan ſhall neuer empty the Lords garner of this graine, though it be no bigger then the ſmalleſt muſtard-ſeede; yet it ſhall grow vp in deſpight of him, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, flouriſh, and be greene for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>3</label> Beſides, are not the faithfull the <hi>Temple of Gods Spirit?</hi> be they not his owne building?<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.19.</note> ſhall hee then ſuffer the corner-ſtone (Faith I meane) to be tumbled out, and beaten to powder? ſhall the Spirit of all truth be accuſed of that, which he condemneth for a ſinne in his Creature? ſhall it be ſaid to him,<note place="margin">Luke 14.30.</note> that <hi>hee began to build and was not able to make an end?</hi> What hinders a houſe begun from perfecting, but, either former igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or want of future ability? ſhall we accuſe the holy Ghoſt of either? Take heede what thou doeſt, <hi>for his wayes are not mans wayes.</hi> Man is blinde and weake, ſo that in proceſſe of time hee may ſee, that the ſcituation of his houſe was not good, the foundation firme, or the modell commendable or vſefull: If all this be well, yet <hi>Sanballats</hi> and <hi>Tobiahs</hi> may preuent him, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty purſue him, ſickeneſſe may ceaze vpon him, that his worke may not be finiſhed. But this builder wee ſpeake of <hi>hee ſeeth all things in one act and together;</hi> he is not,<note place="margin">Semel &amp; ſimul.</note> nor cannot be wiſer at the ſecond thought,<note place="margin">Prou. 11.30.</note> and <hi>what power or wiſedome can preuaile againſt the Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Be thou therefore aſſured, that as the Father
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15197:11"/> (for we in ſpeciall manner appropriate the works of Creation to him) till all was made very good neuer reſted: Nor the Sonne (to whom, in like manner, we attribute the worke of Redemption) vntill it was finiſhed, ceaſed; No more ſhall the Holy Ghoſt (to whom peculiarly we impute the worke of Regeneration) vntill that honourable houſe be perfected, reſt from his labour: for ſhall he not be equall to the other, in himſelfe, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards man, out of himſelfe, for power, wiſedome and goodneſſe? Then hold the one, and grant the other.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>4</label> And finally, may we not draw a reaſon from the ſubiects in whom faith is ſeated to confirme the doctrine? Why? are they not the Elect? doth not that foundation <hi>remaine ſure?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.19. 1 Ioh. 5.18.</note> 
               <hi>Are they not ſuch as he freed from ſinne? that euill one comes not neere them;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7. vlt.</note> 
               <hi>they ſinne not to death; neither with full conſent, or a ſetled reſolution.</hi> What may I more ſay? they pray, reade, and vſe all meanes to preſerue it; ſhall it then die, and wither? No: for if we vſe the meanes, God ſhall conferre a bleſſing.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>1</label> Proceed we now to anſwer an obiection of the Papiſts.<note place="margin">1 I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. 1.19.20.</note> 
               <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus</hi> made <hi>ſhipwracke of faith.</hi> Therefore it may faile finally, totally.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Sol.</note>1. It was no true, but a dead faith. 2. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle (in the iudgement of charity, till they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came open perſecutors, and reuolted from their former profeſſion) deemed that they had faith: And this is the true interpretation, that they ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to haue had faith, but had not any ſound faith at all.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:15197:11"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>2</label> But what ſaith the Ieſuite? hee proceedes a ſtep beyond the Rhemiſh: how could they make (ſaith he) ſhipwracke of that, which they had not?</p>
            <p>Is this manner of ſpeaking ſo ſtrange?<note place="margin">Sol.</note> doth not our Lord ſay, <hi>from him that hath not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 25.29.</note> 
               <hi>euen that he hath ſhall be taken away? Luke</hi> maketh it plaine, ſaying, <hi>That which he ſeemed to haue, ſhall be taken away:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 8.18.</note> Thus doth <hi>Chriſt</hi> reſolue Antichriſt, <hi>Ieſus</hi> the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite. We will omit the like obiections, and ſo make vſe of the doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> And firſt it confuteth the errour of our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, and ſome others that be amongſt vs, who hold, that a man may fall from faith totally. Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſo periſh for euer. But this doctrine (as the Apoſtle ſaith of wiſedome) <hi>is not from aboue, pure, peaceable, and eaſie to be entreated; but from below, ſenſuall, earthly, and diuelliſh;</hi> and therefore (as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh <hi>of Couetouſneſſe) let it not be once named</hi> (except with deteſtation) <hi>amongſt you as becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth Chriſtians.</hi> For variety of faiths exiſtence, doth not preuent the perpetuity of it's eſſence.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> And in the ſecond place, by this doctrine, wee may be informed what to iudge of them, that haue ſeemed to begin in the Spirit, yet ended in the fleſh: Aſſuredly (what ſhew of profeſſion ſoeuer they made) this immortall ſeed was neuer rooted and grounded in their harts. What if <hi>Achitophel</hi> or <hi>Iudas</hi> creepe into the Court, be companion to <hi>Dauid,</hi> and his Lord, take ſweet counſell <hi>with them,</hi> receiue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion from them? yet if they conceiue iniquity, expect opportunity, lift vp their heele againſt <hi>Gods</hi> annointed, and bathe their hands in the blood of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15197:12"/> his deſtruction; (though the Pope and his pole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhorne brethren would canonize them for Saints, engraue their names with great red capitall letters in their Calendars) they are but deepe-headed, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell-hearted Traytors; trees <hi>without fruit, twiſe dead, rent vp by the rootes, and reſerued for the black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of darkeneſſe for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let <hi>Iehu,</hi> march in fury, demand, <hi>is thy heart vpright as mine?</hi> cry, <hi>giue me thine hand;</hi> call, <hi>come ſee what Zeale I haue for the Lord of Hoſtes;</hi> reply, <hi>What peace, whiles the whoredomes and witchcrafts of thy mother Iezabel remaine?</hi> charge, <hi>Caſt that painted fac'd ſtrumpet downe from the window:</hi> Yet if after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, he pace like the ſlugge, burne as the Ice, and his whole heart goe not after (but wholly depart from) <hi>the God of Iſrael;</hi> we may note him by a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, iudge him a proud-ſpirited perſon, and a meere caſt-away.</p>
            <p>Nay, let <hi>Balaam</hi> prophecy, <hi>I ſhall ſee him, but not yet;</hi> bleſſe, <hi>who can tell the duſt of Iacob;</hi> confeſſe, <hi>the eyes that were ſhut vp, haſt thou (Lord) opened;</hi> pray, <hi>let me dye the death of the righteous;</hi> proteſt, that <hi>for a houſe full of gold or ſiluer he cannot paſſe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of God:</hi> notwithſtanding all this, if hee conſult with the ſonne of <hi>Zippor,</hi> conſent (and giue counſell too) to curſe the children of Iſrael; he is but a baſe wiſard, a lewd perſon, of the Serpents brood, and <hi>God,</hi> one day in iuſtice, ſhall pay him his wages.</p>
            <p>Finally; let <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Hermogenes; Philetus, Alexander</hi> and <hi>Demas</hi> preach Chriſt, or profeſſe him, haue their praiſe in the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> ſend ſalutations
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15197:12"/> to the brethren: but if once there come a <hi>New,</hi> wherein their callings ſhall be reiected, or negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, the world embraced, <hi>Paul</hi> perſecuted, and the ſincere preaching of the word by them reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted; they neuer were the owners of true Faith, or good conſcience, comprehended in the couenant of grace, and therefore a day will come, when, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their workes, they ſhall be rewarded. And as we may deeme of ſuch in former times, ſo may we of the like in theſe latter dayes; for it is an eternall Canon, <hi>They went out from vs, becauſe they were not of vs; for if they had beene of vs, they would haue continued with vs. And this</hi> (obſerue) <hi>is come to paſſe, that it might appeare, they were not all of vs,</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.19.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> And <hi>may Faith faint, yet not faile for euer?</hi> Why then here is a ground of comfort to ſuch as in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time haue felt it, though, for the preſent, it be not in their apprehenſion. Tell mee, didſt thou euer beleeue in the Lord? haſt thou giuen this gueſt a nights lodging? art thou ſure thou once hadſt it? then certainely thou haſt it, though for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thou be otherwiſe minded. What if <hi>Iorden</hi> fill not her bankes to the brimme euery morning? <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> ſtirre not in the wombe at each ſeaſon? <hi>Iacob</hi> apprehend not the Lords preſence continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally? Yet, ſhall not the tyde returne? the babe be aliue and borne? and the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Abraham</hi> be in that place? yes of certaine: ſo Faith may not at all times fill the ſoule with ioy, ſpring in the wombe, or be diſcerned in the hearts habitation; notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, it is not dryed vp, nor dead in the mother,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15197:13"/> nor hath tooke his laſt farewell. Faith may not be compared to <hi>Ionah's gourd,</hi> that withereth in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; neither to the <hi>fig-tree,</hi> on which fruit ſhall neuer grow any more; nor is it like the Lilly, <hi>which to day is, and to morrow caſt into the Ouen;</hi> for God will not ſend a worme to ſmite it; Chriſt ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer curſe it, or the Spirit burne it, totally conſume it: The chilling cold of Winter may pinch it; the heate of the Summers ſunne may ſcorch it; and the lightning from aboue, in ſome degree, blaſt it: yet the Spring ſhall reuiue it; the dew from aboue water it; and the South-winde refreſh it. It may be, like gold, tryed in the fire; but it ſhall be found more precious, come foorth the purer, and preſerue the owners of it <hi>vnto praiſe, honour, and eternall ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, at the appearing of Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.7.</p>
            <p>In my meditations I haue ſometimes thought, that <hi>Faith</hi> is like the <hi>Daizie</hi> (a word compounded of <hi>Day</hi> and <hi>Eye</hi>) or <hi>Marigold:</hi> when the Sunne ſets, ſhe ſhuts; when it riſeth, ſhe reuiueth; for by this Planets motion, ſhe is in a diuers eſtate, and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: So when the Sonne of righteouſnes goeth (as it were) beneath the Globe, diſperſeth his beames an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other way; then <hi>Faith</hi> cloſeth it ſelfe, hangeth the head, and it's leaues are contracted: but when he hath fetched his circumference, &amp; ariſeth within our Horizon, ſpreadeth his beames of heate and mercy vpon it; then it ſprouteth vp, openeth and dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it's ſelfe, ſendeth foorth it's pleaſant fumes, to the great content of him or her in whom it is plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: So that I ſay to thee, Be of good comfort; for as <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaid of <hi>Lazarus: It is not dead, but ſleepeth.</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:15197:13"/> Labour therefore to awake it out of this ſlumber, that it may recouer it's former eſtate, doe it's firſt <hi>workes</hi> and better.</p>
            <p>And for thy direction.</p>
            <p n="1">1. See that thou ſettle not thy ſelfe amongſt Mutes, pitch thy tents where the ſiluer Trumpets are ſounded, and <hi>Aarons</hi> bels ring in the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> euery Sabboath.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Liue not with Liquides; beware of lewd companions. If <hi>Peter</hi> come into <hi>Caiphas</hi> his porch, hang his head ouer, and warme his fingers at, the high-Prieſts fire; he will curſe, ſweare, and ſhall (without reprehenſion too) deny his Maſter: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>Saul</hi> will propheſie among the Prophets.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Vp, and be doing; be not idle, either in thy generall or particular calling: who euer fell a ſleepe working, walking?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Doe not feaſt, but faſt; for that will dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh and weaken the fumes of ſinne; hinder theſe drowſie exhalations, preſerue the pores and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trikles of the minde from cloaſure, and giue the liuely ſpirits full paſſage for motion and action: This is the way to awake it, ſleeping; and to keepe it from ſlumbring, being awaked.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>4</label> And in the laſt place, ſeeing true Faith ſhall not finally faile; how ſhould it encourage vs to vſe all mennes that might preſerue it, continue it? It's a falſe dreame, obiected by our aduerſaries, that cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of a thing, makes men careleſſe in the vſe of all helpes, that may further or accompliſh the end: For doth not the Huſband-man plow, ſow, harrow, hedge, riſe early, ſit vp late, eate the bread of ſorrow
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15197:14"/> and carefulneſſe, in the expectation of a good crop of corne at the time of harueſt? Will not the Merchant launch out into the deepe, cut the huge waues and billowes of the Sea, proudly paſſe by the dangerous Rockes, and polling Pyrates, in hope that his Barke ſhall one day returne filled, fraughted with the richeſt Spices? What Patient ſo flegmatique, deſperate, but will ſwallow the moſt bitter pill, ſuppe off the moſt loathſome po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, being before-hand perſwaded, that it will not kill, but cure him? Shall we then be dead on the neſt? want ſpirit? and haue no heart to vſe the meanes that might either beget it, awake it, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue it? Doth not hope of the end ſet all men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke in their ſeuerall proceedings? and ſhall wee haue ſuch a prize as this, in our hands, and haue no hearts? Conſider then what Faith is, and be idle if thou canſt.</p>
            <p>Is not Faith a Prince, that whereſoeuer he pitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Tents is accompanied with royall atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s? Doth it not <hi>purifie the heart?</hi> ſettle and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the ſoule? quench <hi>Sathans darts?</hi> and <hi>ouercome the world?</hi> I ſay more; Faith is the very eſſentiall forme of a Chriſtian: Are we not, by it, from all other perſons diſtinguiſhed? what action good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, but from it, as it proper cauſe, hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded? By faith we are enliued, moued, iuſtified and finally ſaued. Therefore heare, reade, pray, conferre, and receiue daily the ſignes and ſeales of thy Maſters comming, the very foode and nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it; out-face ſinne, out-liue ſinne; ſeeing thou art aſſured, that thy labour is not loſt, vaine in the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15197:14"/> Lord. And thus wee proceede to anſwer an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection that ſome might caſt in the way.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> If Faith neuer faile, then it continues for euer? </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> Some hold it ends at death; others at the day of iudgement, becauſe all things till then (as the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the body, the revnion of the ſoule, and fulneſſe of glory) are not in perfect viſion; And we want not thoſe who thinke, that it abideth for all eternity. In briefe, I anſwer; that it ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer faile thee, or forſake thee, ſo long as it may make for the glory of thy God, and the good of thy ſoule. So let vs come more directly to the words themſelues, where we note this ſecond In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, that</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>God guideth man in his ſpirituall iourney.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There be inferiour and ſubordinate leaders, but in this voyage the Lord is the principall conductor; we may all of vs thus farre ſafely confeſſe with <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 24.13.</note> that <hi>We cannot paſſe the commandement of the Lord, to doe good of our owne minde.</hi> And that which the Prophet ſpeaketh of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> or <hi>Aſhur,</hi> may be in generall applied to all the ſons of <hi>Adam; The way of man is not in himſelfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 10.13.</note> 
               <hi>neither is it in man to direct his owne ſteps. Dauid</hi> knew it well, as you may ſee in the 119. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> the point proued neere 119. times: and <hi>Paul</hi> about to trauell with his friends to <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> praieth,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>Now God euen the Father of our Lord C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riſt, guide our iourney vnto you:</hi> and how ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily may Reaſons be brought to confirme it?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> Why? hath not man the eye of his minde put out?<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.14.</note> is he not borne with a veile ouer his vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding? h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w can he then finde out the right way? or
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15197:15"/> diſcerne betwixt pathes that differ? If any demand, how came th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ſtrange thing to paſſe; wee may truely anſwer;<note place="margin">Rom 3.11.23.</note> 
               <hi>Our Parents haue ſinned, and wee too (in them) ſo that wee are all borne blinde: Ionathans</hi> eye waxed dimme by faſting, but ours, and our fathers too,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.12.</note> were cleane put out by feaſting. And <hi>though Man be in honour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 49 <hi>vlt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>yet he hath no vnderſtanding, but is like the periſhing beaſt.</hi> Euery man is a mole.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> Againe, hath he any power to trauell? is he not lame too? are not his anckle-bones crooked, and the feet of his affections turned backeward? The Creeple, who lay at the poole of <hi>Betheſda,</hi> was no more vnable to ſtep into the water of himſelfe; then we to walke in the pathes that lead to the kingdome of heauen: we muſt firſt be cured and healed. Therefore the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſo often (as one that had experience of his owne infirmitie) prayeth. <hi>Giue me the Spirit of life and power,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.32.37.</note> and, <hi>Then ſhall I runne the way of thy comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndements, when thou haſt ſet my heart at liberty.</hi> That ſinne, which put out our eyes, hath alſo depriued vs of ſtrength, ſo that we cannot creepe or crawle in this our ſpirituall iourney, vntill the Lord bid vs (and giue vs power too) to ariſe, and walke.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>3</label> Moreouer, are not the imaginations of his heart, euill?<note place="margin">Gen 65.</note> hath hee power ſo <hi>much as to thinke a good thought?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.5.</note> can he of himſelfe ſtudy to find out the way? No: <hi>he will not giue his mind to turne vnto his God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ 5 4 Ier. 6.16.</note> 
               <hi>he ſaith in his heart, I will none of thy pathes; I will not</hi> (and yet he cannot if he would) <hi>walke therein.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.16.</note> 
               <hi>For it is not in him that willeth, or in him that runneth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut in God that ſheweth mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:15197:15"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>4</label> Adde to all this, that he is poſſeſt with the ſpirit of errour: and what will you ſay then? can ye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie the truth of the doctrine? Alas!<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.2. 1 Tim. 2.26.</note> doth not <hi>Satan rule in the ſonnes of men? take them captiue at his owne will? and leade them at his pleaſure to the land of darkeneſſe?</hi> And let none obiect and ſay; that theſe things are onely ſo <hi>in the children of diſobedience:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.9.</note> for the beſt man doth but know <hi>in part, beleeue in part,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.17. &amp; 7.9. Gal. 5.17.</note> 
               <hi>and is but healed in part;</hi> and who (<hi>Chriſt</hi> onely excepted) that hath not in his beſt condition been led out of the way? plodded ſome by-path? yea, ſtumbled, fallen, and wounded himſelfe in this his pilgrimage? for no ſooner can any, get the leaſt peepe of light, but <hi>Sathan</hi> clappes on a vaile; gather any ſtrength, but he labours to weaken it; or haue ſo much as a minde to returne to his heauenly countrey, but he hales him on, by power, policy, or ſome pleaſant obiect, as the Shepheard or But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher doth the poore lambe by a greene branch in his hand, from the fold, and it's bleating Dam, vnto the houſe of ſlaughter and deſtruction: So that this point is true concerning all perſons. Shall we make ſome vſe of the ſame?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> And here alſo is confuted another point of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, which would make man the firſt mouer of himſelfe in this his heauenly voyage. They haue certaine diſtinctions, as <hi>ex congruo, ex condigno:</hi> and compare a man to him that went from <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to <hi>Iericho, and fell amongſt theeues;</hi> (indeed this Text,<note place="margin">Luke 10.30.</note> and wee too, are fallen among Theeues) for ſay they, The eye of the mind is but dimmed, the will wounded, and the ſoule weakned: but <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15197:16"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:15197:16"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:15197:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:15197:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:15197:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:15197:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:15197:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:15197:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:15197:20"/> 
               <hi>Without me ye can doe nothing;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh 15.5. Eph. 2 1.</note> and his diſciples, that <hi>we are dead;</hi> Now all men know, that hee who is dead, can neither ſee, heare, ſpeake, moue, or doe any thing. And whether it be more ſafe to credit <hi>Paul,</hi> or the Pope; <hi>Ieſus,</hi> or the Ieſuite, iudge you.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>1</label> But, ſay they, why then doth God command what we cannot doe?</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Sol.</note>1. That we may take knowledge of our owne weakeneſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Flee to him for power.</p>
            <p>And 3. becauſe hee giues his ſpirit with his precept, therefore we muſt be called vpon.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>2</label> Againe they obiect, ſaying; How can God in Iuſtice puniſh vs, if wee haue no power to obey?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Solut.</note>Well enough: for had we not power in <hi>Adam,</hi> and loſt it? Thus ſhall God <hi>be true, and euery man a lyar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> And is God <hi>mans principall guide?</hi> Here then is matter of thankſgiuing, to all that be in a good condition, and are ſet and ſetled vpon a Rocke, and ſure foundation:<note place="margin">Iob. 10.10. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Who powred thee out like milke? thickened thee like curdes? cloathed thee with skin and fleſh? gaue thee life and grace? and preſerued thy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 22.9.10.</note> 
               <hi>Who lead thee in ſafety out of the wombe?</hi> why mighteſt not thou haue periſhed with thouſands in that perilous paſſage, and thy mothers body haue become thy ſepulchre?</p>
            <p>But I will turne my ſpeech to you that haue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and iudge you what I ſay.</p>
            <p>Who guided thee into the vnſearchable path of that hidden decree, out of which ſo many millions are excluded? Who found out, that new and euer
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15197:20"/> liuing way, when thou, by thy ſinne, hadſt ſhut vp that good olde way, that leadeth to heauen? how comes it to paſſe that thy Parents were beleeuers, there being at this day ſo many ſons of Infidels? tell me, if thou canſt, the true reaſon, that the word of truth hath run to and fro neere thy habitation? how is it, that thou art turned to heauen-ward, &amp; ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny be going backward? if thy ſelf be conuerted, who directed that ſpeech in the congregation, publiſhed to all, that it ſhould open thy vnderſtanding, boare thy eare that was cloſed, &amp; bend thy rebellious will to obey the pathes of thoſe diuine precepts? why were not others, as well as thy ſelfe, thus wrought vpon? are thy ſteps ſtraight, others crooked? art thou ſeparated, many hardned? Is thy face towards <hi>Syon?</hi> thy garments not defiled by falling? and is thy courſe to the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> the new Ieruſalem? why then boaſt not, preſume not, but confeſſe it is the Lords owne worke, and let it be maruellous in thine eyes: breake out into thankſgiuing, confeſſe, that it is the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> that hath wrought theſe great workes for thee, by thee.</p>
            <p>I haue ſeene this euill, amongſt many, vnder the Sunne; that ſauing graces are but accounted as common fauours, generall gifts; and to be in the path to heauen, reputed as an ordinary benefit; ſuch as haue had their eyes to ſee, eares to heare, and feet to runne, eſteeme theſe things as no great bleſſings; but this argueth an ingratefull minde, and graceleſſe heart: So, to haue the eye of the vnderſtanding opened, the eare of the ſoule boared, and the feete of the affection, to runne
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15197:21"/> aright, prepared, be not eſteemed, or, as they ought, regarded: And is not this forgetfulneſſe, ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, and a ſinne to be for euer abandoned? Take vp words therefore of praiſe, admiration; Make a ſong,<note place="margin">Exod. 10.1.</note> with <hi>Moſes,</hi> for this thy great deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: confeſſe with <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> that the Lord ſent thee this iourney; Ne, breake out with <hi>Dauid, Lord, thou haſt bin my God and guide, from my mothers wombe;</hi> or with <hi>Ieremiah, it's thy endleſſe mercy I was not long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe conſumed.</hi> Yea, let this alwayes be thy long; <hi>I was as a ſheepe going aſtray,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. <hi>vlt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>but by the hand of my God. I am now turned to the ſhepheard and Biſhop of my ſoule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a vſe worthy the preſſing, amplifying; and loath am I thus to leaue it; yet this little that I haue ſaid, may giue you iuſt occaſion to ſearch more deepely into the matter: onely I wil adde one thing. Wouldeſt thou ſee the wonderfull goodneſſe of God towards thee, in this thy pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage? why then, looke backe ſo farre as the very beginning of this thy iourney, which is at thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception; labour to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the dangers that thou waſt ſubiect vnto, and haſt eſcaped: conſider what euils haue befallen many of thy fellow-trauellers; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the diſtinct acts of Gods prouidence ouer thee in particular; (and then be vnthankefull, if thou canſt;) for this is the way, and I cannot giue thee a better: And ſo we come to another vſe of the doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>Doth God guide man in his ſpirituall iourney?</hi> Here then we muſt learne a l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſon of patience, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and ſubiection, and that for our perſons,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15197:21"/> actions. Art thou with <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſold into Egypt? murmure not, the Lord may haue done it, to ſaue many a liue. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> muſt take the Babe and be gone; Why? <hi>Herod</hi> is not yet dead, that ſeekes the childes life. <hi>Abraham</hi> muſt trudge, hee knowes not whither; What thoe? ſhall not the Lord be with him? <hi>Iacob</hi> muſt to Padan-Aram, for doth not his brother threaten to kill him? Aſſure thy ſelfe, that if thou be guided by God, thou ſhalt neuer be led into danger; or dwell longer in a bad place, or ſtrange countrey, then ſhall be good for thee: For the preſent thou maieſt doubt of it, but the end ſhall declare it. Murmure not, repine not, like the old Iewes, in this thy iourney, be content with thy preſent habitation; follow Gods hand, to what place ſoeuer he ſhall call thee; haue an eye to the cloude and <hi>pillar</hi> of his <hi>proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence;</hi> and though thou ſeeme to goe from home, thou goeſt towards home; out of the way, thou goeſt the ſafeſt way, and thy end ſhall be bleſſed for God, as he was with <hi>Dauid,</hi> ſhall be with thee, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-ſoeuer thou goeſt, and he ſhall reſt where thou doeſt, though (peraduenture like <hi>Iacob</hi>) thou art not aware of it.</p>
            <p>Againe, takeſt thou any thing in hand, and doth it not proſper according to the deſired expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? be not impatient, for he that guideth thee, guideth all thy actions, and directeth them to their proper ends. <hi>Dauid</hi> did confeſſe, that God ſent <hi>Shimei to curſe him:</hi> and <hi>in trouble,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 39 9.</note> hee would <hi>holde his peace,</hi> becauſe <hi>the Lord had done it.</hi> The Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may ſearch into the nature of the diſeaſe,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15197:22"/> adminiſter the choiſeſt ingredients, temper and mixe them with great skill, obſerue time, and all conuenient circumſtances: yet for all this, if God giue not a bleſſing, old <hi>Chancers</hi> rule holds, <hi>Then farewell Phyſicke;</hi> For God is aboue Nature, who firſt made Nature of nothing. Wee muſt all doe this in our ſeuerall callings; vſe wee the meanes, and referre the ſucceſſe to the Lord; imitating that religious reſolute Woman, who after pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and faſting thus concluded;<note place="margin">Eſter 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>Now if I periſh, I periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>4</label> And in the laſt place; let it teach vs all to runne to the Lord, to be guided by him; and to commit our ſelues and waies to be gouerned of him. All the faithfull haue done this, in all their proceedings; why then ſhould not we imitate them? What man, if he be to goe a long and vnknowne iourney, will not hire a guide to conduct him? or to vndertake a voyage by water, to the Eaſt-Indies, Guiana, or the New-found-land, but deſireth the moſt skilfull Pilot to goe with him? And ſhall not wee ſeeke vnto God, deſire his direction from earth to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen? from this old Egypt, to the new Ieruſalem? If we doe not, we may well wander out ot our way, and ſplit the ſhip of our ſoules vpon the rocke of condemnation.</p>
            <p>And becauſe men, naturally, are not prone to put this point in practiſe; take theſe following mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues to further thee in thy duty.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Who is it, that thou art to depend vpon for direction? Is it not he that formed thee at the firſt, and whom thou doeſt confeſſe to be thy Father?
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15197:22"/> who then would offend ſo good a <hi>God,</hi> ſo mercifull a Creatour, Gouernour? tread vnder-foote the <hi>Lord of life,</hi> and haue no care to walke after his ſteps? Shall we not follow the Sonnes example, who learned obedience of his Father? muſt the holy Ghoſt not be obeyed, whoſe invitements are more worth then all the world? Is it ſo, that his motions muſt be reſiſted, and the Spirit of all truth wearied, grieued? Take heede what thou doeſt, for if we put this guide farre from vs, he will not be fetcht againe (as the prouerbe is) <hi>with a we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> finger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Againe, is not mans life ſhort? vncertaine too? why ſhould wee then omit the ſeaſon, let ſlip the preſent oportunity? Dayes will not be redeemed, time recalled: Miſerable experience haue wee of ſome, who putting off the occaſion offred, were neuer reclaimed. <hi>Lots</hi> ſonnes thought their father mocked, and were they not ſuddenly deſtroyed? <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> would not attend the day of her viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but what became of her? <hi>Iezabel</hi> had a time to turne, but would not; was ſhee not ſuddenly caſt <hi>into a be ſorrow?</hi> Therefore vp, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell to little <hi>Zoar; Come out of Babel,</hi> and what thou haſt to doe, doe with all thy power; leaſt thou want time, when thou maieſt be willing. The rich Glutton in hell, then would haue had his brethren inſtructed; poſſibly hee would (had hee beene aliue againe) haue hyred a Preacher; But, hee that may and will not, when hee would hee ſhall not.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the third place; let the example of others
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15197:23"/> and their ſucceſſe alſo, moue thee to runne vnto the Lord. How did the lame, blinde, deafe, and dumbe ſ eke to our Sauiour? and was their labour loſt? Goe to God therefore, and ſay, <hi>Lord open mine e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſleepe not in death: Heale me, for I am ſore wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> Conuert me, and I ſhall be conuerted.</hi> You that are Parents, take your ſonnes and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters by the hand, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll downe before God, and cry, <hi>Lord be mercifull to this my childe; for he falleth often in the fire, and is miſerably ſeduced by the Diuell.</hi> Let Maſters imitate the good <hi>Centurion,</hi> and deſire God to recouer their ſeruants. Shall they thus call and cry for the infirmities of the body? and ſhall wee take no paines for the deſperate diſeaſes of our ſoules? Weepe we, pray we therefore for our ſelues and for our children; and no doubt but the Lord will heare vs, helpe vs: And what a ioy will this be, when they and we ſhall returne home againe, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, walking? But alas! our words take no im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, becauſe men thinke they haue no neede of the Phyſition.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Moreouer, doe but weigh well in thy minde what a miſery it is, to be out of the way; we pitty a poore Traue ler, that hath miſt his path, and ſeeme to take compaſſion on him: And yet we by others harmes cannot learne to beware. <hi>Chriſt</hi> (I cannot tell what others m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y) did account this a fearefull condition; and makes it a reaſon to moue the people for to walke in the light; theſe be his words,<note place="margin">Iob. 12.35.</note> 
               <hi>Leaſt ye goe, ye cannot tell whither.</hi> If a man doe but ſet his face towards ſome ſteepe rocke, or deepe draw well, oh, how will wee cry aloud that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15197:23"/> he might returne! Is this ſo fearefull? Then by earthly dangers, learne to auoide Hels damnation.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Beſides, conſider where we ſhall arriue if we be not guided by God? Is it at <hi>Samaria?</hi> ſhall we finde a Prophet there, that will feede vs with bread and water? No, we ſhall not haue one drop to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh vs, after our iourneyes end. Wee count that mans condition wretched, that fals amongſt Theeues, or that is caſt into priſon; But whoſe eares will not tingle, and heart tremble, to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at what a dolefull hauen wicked perſons (if they turne not) ſhall one day be landed? Neuer had any earthly Traueller, ſo cold entertainment: But wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men are vnwiſe; therefore they thinke not of their latter end, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.29.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And in the laſt place, adde to all this, that they ſhall not <hi>depart thence, till they haue paid the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt farthing;</hi> and that will be neuer: Was it a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous iudgement to be captiue 70. yeares in <hi>Babilon?</hi> Did <hi>Dauid</hi> complaine, and cry, <hi>Woe is me, that hee dwelt a few dayes in Meſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ek and Kedar?</hi> What will it be then, to be <hi>bound hand and foote, caſt into vtter darkeneſſe, with the Diuell and his damned Angels?</hi> If they that goe to this place of darkeneſſe, might but hang their Harpes vpon the Willowes; in ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of heart thinke on <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> as many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of yeares as there be S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arres in the heauen, drops of water in the great Ocean, or graines of ſand in the earths whole Globe and then haue hope to returne, it might be ſome mitigation of torment; But their eyes ſhall faile with waiting to returne, yet they ſhall neuer be returned: <hi>Conſider this there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15197:24"/> yee that forget God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 50.22.</note> 
               <hi>leaſt hee teare you in peices, and there be none to deliuer you.</hi> And thus hauing finiſhed this Point, wee come to gather a third, which is, that</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>Thoſe that be guided by God, are guided by his word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> obeyed not the Law, are they not ſaid to <hi>forſake the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 10.6.</note> 
               <hi>and not to ſerue him?</hi> and when they had no <hi>Prieſt to teach, or Law</hi> to direct,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 15.3.</note> were they not <hi>all that ſeaſon without the true God?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 20.32.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> (at his laſt farewell) <hi>commends his friends to God, and the word of his grace; Dauid</hi> often prayeth <hi>to be guided by his precepts:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 5.8. Malac. 4.4.</note> Doth not <hi>Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chi</hi> conclude, <hi>Remember the Law of Moſes, with the ſtatutes and iudgements?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> Firſt, becauſe <hi>Vrim</hi> and <hi>Thummim,</hi> dreames &amp; vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, mirac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es and extraordinary motions, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate irradiations of the ſpirit are ceaſed. <hi>In old time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1.1.</note> 
               <hi>at ſeuerall times, and in diuers manners the Lord ſpake to his children;</hi> for then the word was not perfectly and fully written. The Apoſtles too, had dreames and viſions in their dayes; for they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing their calling vpon the very border of the Law, and commiſſion too, to <hi>preach to all Nations,</hi> had neede of them; otherwiſe their Doctrine would not haue beene ſo well credited, neither they haue vnderſtood (hauing no reuealed rule of direction) to what Townes or Cities,<note place="margin">Acts 16.9.</note> eſpecially, they ſhould haue preached.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> Againe, may not God and his word, as the end and goodneſſe of a thing, be conuerted? In many thing,<note place="margin">Rom 7.12.</note> I am ſure they may. <hi>God is holy, and iuſt, and good:</hi> and is not his word the ſame? hee is <hi>true, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15197:24"/> faithfull, and no accepter of perſons:</hi> may we not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the like of his word? What God commands, it commands; what he wils, it wils; what he intends, it intends; and if the word haue a Quarrell with thee (note this:<note place="margin">Rom. 7.7.8.</note>) the Lord hath a Quarrell with thee; for they are not contrary Maſters, but agree in all things. And ſo I paſſe briefly to the Vſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> Where firſt wee are to checke the Papiſts, and confute a third point of their Doctrine; who take away the word from the common people: Is not this to depriue them of God, to make them like the auncient <hi>Gentiles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>ſtrangers from the common weale of Iſrael,</hi> and meere <hi>Atheiſts?</hi> Truely it is no better: who is ſo blinde that ſeeth it not? or ſo incredulous, that beleeues it not? Inſtead of the Law, they muſt haue Traditions; a Picture, for the Goſpell of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Did not the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when they left the law, <hi>work wickednes, forſake God, and ſerued him not?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 15 3. &amp;c.</note> And for this thing are they not ſaid to haue <hi>followed Baalim</hi> and <hi>Aſhtaroth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudges 10.6.</note> 
               <hi>and the gods of the children of Ammon?</hi> Be not therfore deceiued; for theſe Papiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Prieſts, world compaſſing Ieſuites, are but wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring planets, blinde pilots; after whom whoſoeuer ſhall ſaile the ſhip of his ſoule, ſhall ſplit her, at the day of his diſſolution, vpon the rocke of that dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous poſition; and then what can follow, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall condemnation? I haue wondered at theſe mens madnes: for the knowledge of the rule is of abſolute neceſſity in all arts or functions, to the wel-doing of an action: For example: Can a Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner rightly guide his ſhip thorow the ſea, without the knowledge of Card and Compaſſe? The Carpenter
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15197:25"/> build a houſe in comely order, being ignorant of that patterne, by which it is to be framed? Or a ſchoole-boy ſpeake exact phraſe and true Latine, and haue no vnderſtanding in the precepts of Grammar? And yet in the moſt curious worke theſe deceiuing guides would haue vs want the Rule:<note place="margin">Exod. 31 3. 1 Kings 7.</note> This is <hi>not to iudge righteous iudgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> Againe, this meeteth with thoſe ſpirits, that ſtand all vpon Reuelations, immediate motions; who ſay that, <hi>No Chriſtian ſhould take his ground firſt from the word, but the Spirit; for the Diuell alleadgeth Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and doth wreſt it to his purpoſe.</hi> But poore ſoules! theſe know not of <hi>what ſpirit they themſelues are.</hi> would aske ſuch a man this Queſtion; How can he diſcerne the motion of the ſpirit to be from the Spirit? He will anſwere, Becauſe it's good, and tends to holineſſe; Well: how can he tell what is good, or euill? muſt he not goe to the Rule to try it? Theſe would ſee the image of God without a glaſſe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand truth, before they heare it vttered: Alas! <hi>profeſsing themſelues to be wiſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1 22</note> 
               <hi>they are become fooles.</hi> For what a ſtrange Poſition is this (if it be true, that came lately to my hands) how that <hi>Grace being once wrought in the heart, the ſpirit aboliſheth all former knowledge?</hi> and they bid <hi>Away withall Scripture know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</hi> Theſe will try the ſpirits (I feare) till a lying ſpirit poſſeſſe them.<note place="margin">1 Tim <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 5.</note> 
               <hi>Let vs therefore beware of</hi> (if we know any) <hi>ſuch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> And in the next place, <hi>if they that be guided by God, are guided by his word;</hi> we are informed what to thinke of all thoſe, that liue in palpable, more then Egyptian darkeneſſe; who neither know God, or
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15197:25"/> vnderſtand any one ſentence in the ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Is not their eſtate fearefull? who is theſe mens guide? ſurely <hi>Sathan, ſinne, and the faſhions of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that (if God giue the bleſſing) I might a little moue theſe people to <hi>come out of Babilon;</hi> and fire them (as it were, like <hi>Ioab</hi> to <hi>Abſalom</hi>) to returne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their God; Let them heare what iudgements haue befallen the ignorant, what be threatned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them that tread theſe darke ſteps.</p>
            <p>Did not the people of God, goe into Captiuity,<note place="margin">Iſai 5.13.</note> 
               <hi>for want of knowledge?</hi> Say, this was but a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall puniſhment, yet it had a curſe with it. And how doth the Lord complaine,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>My people are cut off for want of knowledge?</hi> We count it a miſerable thing, and it cauſes wringing of the hands, folding of the armes, and many a teare ſhed, when we ſee, at the Aſſiſes, a proper man caſt away, hauing had his Booke, &amp; could not one word by art, or tell a letter: Oh, ſay we! he might haue beene ſaued, if he could haue read: But what a day will that be, when all ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant men and women, muſt hold vp their hand at the Tribunall Throne of Chriſt, and be cut off, <hi>and caſt into vtter darkeneſſe,</hi> becauſe <hi>they knew not him,</hi> or his <hi>Goſpell?</hi> Therefore, thou that art igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and heareſt me this day; <hi>Get knowledge, get vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding;</hi> for if thou dye in this condition, thou ſhalt dye the ſecond and eternall death. Why? hath not <hi>Chriſt</hi> threatned to <hi>come in flaming fire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 1.7.8. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>to render vengeance vpon all that know him not, and obey not his Goſpell?</hi> Did not the Prophet imprecate, that the Lord would <hi>poure out his fury vpon ſuch as knew him</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 10. <hi>vlt.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:15197:26"/> 
               <hi>not, and the families, that called not on his Name?</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not (by the way) but commend you, in that you haue gotten guides: but, <hi>Learne the Law at their mouthes;</hi> practiſe what is deliuered; ſquare your actions by this word; ſo <hi>ſhall it goe well with you at your latter end.</hi> But if for all this, you will walke in darkneſſe (be not deceiued) one day to <hi>darkneſſe ye ſhall goe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Io. 12.35. Iude 13.</note> for, <hi>if it be eternall life to know God, and whom he hath ſent;</hi> then by the rule of contraries, <hi>How ſhall the ignorant eſcape the damnation of hell?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Io. 17 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>4</label> Laſt of all; Is this Doctrine a truth? then here is comfort, and tidings of great encouragement to all ſuch as are guided by the word. Caſt not off this yoake, breake not theſe bonds aſunder, what ſcoffes ſoeuer thou receiue of the world: Let them play, but doe thou pray: let them ſhuffle the cards, ſearch thou the Scriptures: let them ſit at home, and goe to Dice and Tables; goe thou to heare the word in the publique Congregation: For I am ſure, the one is lawfull; the other (at the beſt) is doubtfull: And for my owne part, I wiſh neither to approue, or practiſe matters of that nature. I ſay therefore to all ſuch, be not weary in ſo doing: Caſt not the ſtatutes of God behinde your backes; neither be abaſhed to liue by the booke; for to liue by Gods booke, is to liue by his command, and he that doth ſo, ſhall neuer be aſhamed. The braue men of our dayes may laugh you to ſcorne, thinke it too much preciſeneſſe, rend the booke of God, like the vaile of the Temple, from the top to the bottome: But when death draweth neere the doores, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall call vs to an account, I doubt not but ſuch
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15197:26"/> will wiſh, they had had a greater care to haue wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in thy ſteps; and with all their hearts would change their owne for thy condition: But till then, thou canſt not apprehend the rich fruit of thy wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings; neither they, the fearefull effects that ſhall follow their wandrings.</p>
            <p>And now the fourth and laſt doctrine to be handled, we gather from the Connexion or knit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting together of the parts; which is, that</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>4</label> 
               <hi>They, who (here on Earth) are guided by Gods Counſell, ſhall (when their changing comes) be receiued into Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They, and none but they.<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed is the man</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>that doth not walke in the counſell of the wicked, nor ſtand in the way of ſinners, nor ſit in the ſeate of the ſcornefull: But hath his delight in the Law of Iehouah: and in his Law doth meditate day and night.</hi> And is this <hi>Bleſſedneſſe</hi> perfect here on earth? No:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.9.10. &amp;c. Pſal. 16. <hi>vlt.</hi>
               </note> why then, they ſhall haue it <hi>in the fulneſſe thereof, in the world to come.</hi> Are we not bid to <hi>inquire of the old way, which is the good way, and to walke therein,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier 6.16.</note> 
               <hi>and wee ſhall find reſt to our ſoules? Reſt,</hi> not corporall or tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall; but ſpirituall, and eternall may well be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood; for <hi>they that die in the Lord, are ſaid to reſt from their labours.</hi> But this point is more eaſily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, then credited; and better beleeued, then pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed: yet take a Reaſon or two, further to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the one, and perſwade the other.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> Why? is not Gods word and counſell, the plaine path and rode way to the kingdome of glory?<note place="margin">Prou. 2.10.11. &amp; 3.15.16 17.18.</note> He that would trauell to <hi>London,</hi> if he find out the true way and walke therein, ſhall he not come to it at
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15197:27"/> the laſt? for the City will not be remoued: So hee that doth know the right path to this <hi>Countrey, which is aboue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor 9.26. 2 Tim. 4.7.8.</note> let him trauell on therein, and he ſhal aſſuredly come to it, at his iourneyes end. God will not giue his children a crooked rule.</p>
            <p>There be but two things for to conduct vs to this Kingdome; and are not both expreſly conteined in his Counſell?<note place="margin">Ioh 3.16.</note> The one is, <hi>To beleeue in Chriſt,</hi> for ſo we be iuſtified,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.1.</note> and placed in the right path: The other is, <hi>The precept,</hi> after which if wee walke, wee ſhall certainly finiſh our iourney with Glory.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> Againe, the Lord is true of his promiſe, he cannot deny himſelfe;<note place="margin">Ioſh. 21. <hi>vlt.</hi> 2 Tim. 2.13.</note> therefore if we keepe the condition, the Lord will accompliſh what he hath promiſed. If any man ſhould ſay vnto me, <hi>Sir,</hi> inquire the way that leades to my houſe; and come to my home, and you ſhall haue all kinde entertainment; Now if I ſhould accompliſh his command, in ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the path, and paſſe on vntill I come to his habitation; what if then I be not entertained? were not the fault in him that promiſed me this kindnes? But God is not like man; for let vs walke towards heauen till death, the Gates of heauen ſhall not be ſhut,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.24.</note> but open; for <hi>faithfull is he that hath promiſed, who will alſo doe it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> And may not this doctrine firſt informe vs, what to thinke of the beſt Heathen, who euer liued, and many too in our dayes,<note place="margin">Act. 17.30. Gal 6.16. Heb 4 2. 1 P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. 4.17.</note> that were neuer guided by this Rule? For the one ſort, we deny not, but God can worke extraordinarily: but for the other, who <hi>haue had the kingdome of Chriſt come to their doores,</hi> yet would not giue it the leaſt entertainment, or be
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15197:27"/> ruled by it; ſhall we not feare, if not certainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that they are vtterly <hi>depriued of the glory of God?</hi> And I pray, that there might be none ſuch in this place and congregation: But if there be; let that perſon know, that, one day, his ignorance, and careleſſe neglect of the glorious Goſpel, ſhall deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be laid to his charge.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> Beſides, here we are inſtructed in the right way how to be bleſſed for euer. Caſt off therefore the wayes and workes of darkeneſſe; take the narrow path, that leadeth to this eternall weight of glory: Turne, ſeeing the Lord in mercy doth affoord you time and meanes; and be no more ſeduced, or led out of the way, We would all of vs, when our pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage is at an end, be receiued into glory; why then, let vs not <hi>follow the faſhions of this euill world; ſtep after a multitude to doe wickedly; obey ſinne in the luſts of it; or, be guided by the Prince, that ruleth in the children of diſobedience:</hi> But learne the reuealed counſell of the Lord, <hi>take ſtraight ſteps to our feete;</hi> ſo ſhall we, at the time of this our change, be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued from earth into that place, which is full of glory, and that ſhall haue no end. For,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.16.</note> 
               <hi>as many as walke according to this Rule, Peace ſhall be vpon them, with mercy, and vpon the whole Iſrael of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> And may not this encourage all that haue begun well, not to grow weary or faint in the way, but to go on vndaunted, and with a Chriſtian reſolution?</p>
            <p>You therefore that are, or may be Maiors or Gouernours of Townes and Cities: haue you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, with <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> to build and guide the Lords people? why, faint not: let not <hi>ſuch men as you flee;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15197:28"/> goe not into the idols Temple to liue;</hi> let no <hi>burdens be borne on the Sabboath:</hi> ſet peace, and remoue oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion amongſt them committed to your charge; Let not ſinne goe vnpuniſhed; godlineſſe be vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded; or your high callings, by your ſlackneſſe, be abuſed. It was <hi>Dauids</hi> prize and praiſe; not, that the <hi>Lord choſe him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 78.70.</note> 
               <hi>tooke him from the flockes of ſheepe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">71.</note> 
               <hi>following the ewes with yong, to feede Iacob his people, and Iſrael his poſſeſsion:</hi> but in this; that <hi>he fed them according to the perfection of his heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">72.</note> 
               <hi>and led them by the diſcretion of his hands.</hi> He that did this, is now in glory; and they that tread in his ſteps ſhall aſſuredly,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.8.</note> when they haue ended and ſerued (thus) their time, be receiued and glorified with him.</p>
            <p>And you <hi>(Right Worſhipfull,)</hi> whom God hath made great in the Countrey and Common-weale; take heed what ye doe: Let <hi>Ioſhua</hi> his reſolution be yours; whatſoeuer others haue done, or may doe, <hi>Doe you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſh. 24.15.</note> 
               <hi>and your people ſerue the Lord.</hi> It's your goodneſſe, that one day will be your greatneſſe. And ſeeing that you haue receiued much already from the Lord, and haue a further promiſe of a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious crowne and ſcepter, doth it not ſtand with equity, that ſuch as you (aboue all) ſhould take heart to your ſelues, and with more cheerefulneſſe runne the wayes of Gods commands? For will not you your ſelues expect from them the beſt and moſt worke, to whom you giue the greateſt wages? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides conſider, what will your callings or riches profit you one day,<note place="margin">Mat. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>if you ſhould looſe your own ſoules?</hi> Is it, or wil it be any benefit, to haue large poſſeſſions
<pb facs="tcp:15197:28"/> on earth; and not a foot in heauen? high callings; and not to <hi>be called of God?</hi> a wiſe diſputer in this world; and be dumbe before <hi>Chriſt</hi> at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming? cloathed with purple, and fine linnen, and fare delicately euery day; and yet be found naked in the great day of the Lord? Therefore be friends to the word, procure it's liberty to runne, and doe you and yours runne after it too; for this ſhall one day be your beſt portion, and great reward.</p>
            <p>And you that are of the tribe of Leui, and my brethren: Let me exhort you, as one vnfit to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct you, that you would <hi>quit you like men, and be ſtrong: Preach in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon:</hi> pull out all the arrowes of Gods mercy and iudgement, forth of the Quiuers of the Law and Goſpell; draw them betwixt the armes of power, and a ſound minde; looſe them from the finger of affection, let them flie with a will: and then intreat the Lord, ſo to guide them, that, like the ſword of <hi>Saul,</hi> and bow of <hi>Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi> they may neuer returne to your hands empty. Be heard aboue, &amp; ſeene below; let your liues ſhine before your doctrine, as the lightning doth precede the Thunder; ſo will your words pierce the dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and cauſe your people quake and ſhudder amidſt the Congregation. <hi>Haue care of the flockes, ouer which the Holy Ghoſt hath made you ouer-ſeers;</hi> for this wil be your ioy at your iourneys end, when you can truely ſay, <hi>I haue coueted no mans ſiluer or gold, I haue deliuered the whole counſell of God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 20.26.27.28.33.</note> 
               <hi>and am free from the blood of all men.</hi> And when <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall come <hi>(who after a little while will come)</hi> be able to preſent your flocke, as a pure Virgine to him,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15197:29"/> ſpotleſſe,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.27.</note> blameleſſe. He that doth this, ſhall <hi>ſhine as the Sunne for euer and euer;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 12.3.</note> but hee that is care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, muſt vndergoe a heauy account, a fearefull reckoning.</p>
            <p>And in concluſion, that which I haue ſaid to one, I ſay to all; Learne, learne this leſſon; ſet before you the glory prepared for you, and though you finde rubs in the way, out-skip them all; for your <hi>death ſhall be better then the day wherein you are borne;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12 2. &amp;c.</note> and the time of Chriſts ſecond comming, of more worth then all the world. Trauellers muſt not conceiue what they, for the preſent, are, being in a ſtrange countrey; but what they ſhall be, when they come vnto their friends, and eternall home; for that will cheere the ſad heart, refreſh the decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſpirits, cauſe a man to truſſe vp the loines of his minde, and be trudging. Remember then, that thou caſt thine eye forward, peepe within the vaile, and ſtedfaſtly thinke on the royall entertainment at thy iourneyes end.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>4</label> And ſhall they that are guided by Gods coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell be receiued vnto glory? May we not then ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a ground of comfort to ſtay vs from immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate mourning for the faithfull departed?<note place="margin">1 Theſ 4.13. &amp;c.</note> I will therefore apply it to the preſent occaſion. Be of good comfort for your friend deceaſed: ſhe is not dead, but ſleepeth, and is at reſt from her labours; her fight is well fought, and ſhe is diuiding the ſpoile.</p>
            <p>But becauſe of all things, immoderate affection vpon the like occaſion, hath too much accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Gods beſt children; I will (as much as in me is)
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15197:29"/> giue you ſome preſeruatiues to preuent or expell a hopeleſſe, and (not to be endured) heartleſſe mourning.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Why? what is ſhe tooke from? and what is the world and all therein, but <hi>Vanity and vexation of ſpirit?</hi> Is it not a <hi>Sodom,</hi> where men burne in luſt? an Egypt, where Iſrael is burthened by the vnmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Taske-maſters? a Babylon, where the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Iew hangs his Harpe vpon the Willowes, and ſingeth his <hi>Hebrew</hi> ſongs in a ſtrange land? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſhall I further liken it? Why, to an Hoſpitall, where be both deafe, dumbe, lame and blinde; a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Peſthouſe, where be many ſicke of euery ſoare, die of each diſeaſe: Doth not the purple, red and ſcarlet tokens of ſinne, that preſage a certaine and a ſecond death, breake out daily amongſt the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants? Truely, it's a very Bedlem, peſtered with fooles, filled with madde and franticke fellowes; who know not, either their owne miſery, or can endure to be cured by the bottomeleſſe depth of Gods mercy: In a word, it's a ſinke, a whirle-poole and colluvies of all vncleanneſſe. Shall wee then grieue, ſigh and torment our ſelues, that our friends are remoued from ſo bad, and no better, an habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
            <p>Take a ſtrict view of this world in her greateſt beauty, being cloathed with greene, white, red and ſcarlet, with all variety of the choiſeſt colours; the Rabbets and Lambes skipping and leaping in the pleaſant valleyes; the fiſhes ſwimming and playing in the ſiluer-hewed ſtreames of the pureſt waters; the birds ſinging and pruning themſelues
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15197:30"/> on the ſprigs, and tops of the hills and mountaines; euery branch bearing fruit; each hearbe and flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ſending forth her ſweeteſt ſmell of perfume: yet will not one pinching froſt, Northren blaſt, or ſcorching heate, rent her purple Robe, wither her tender face, wrinckle her ſmootheſt brow, and ſpoile her cleane of her well-tempered complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? ſo that her rich attire and comely gloſſe, will but carry a cold report to the inhabitants heart (as <hi>Ioſephs party-coloured coate,</hi> torne and all be-blouded did to old <hi>Iacob</hi> his father) being repreſented be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and be a meane to bring amaine, his gray or gay haires vnto the Graue.</p>
            <p>But alas! we conſider not, how <hi>the faſhion of this world goeth away:</hi> we iudge better of it, then ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues by farre, and ſo, through miſ-apprehenſion, we <hi>pierce our ſelues through with needleſſe ſorrowes.</hi> We ſend our ſonnes from countrey to Court, from England to Ireland, in the naked expectation of ſome better preferment; and yet weepe, mourne and bawle, that our friends are gone from earth to heauen; and from forreiners in a poore cottage, to be the chiefeſt ſubiects in a glorious kingdome.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Againe, is not Heauen a <hi>houſe, where be many man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions?</hi> and ſhall the Lord thereof want inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants? muſt ſuch ſeats be empty &amp; not repleniſhed? why then; ſhould he not looſe the end and fruit of his creation? <hi>Dauids</hi> roome muſt not be voyde for euer; but at the time appointed, by his own perſon ſupplied. We muſt all of vs, in our turnes, vp to this <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> our High Prieſt, will not haue vs abſent: Heauen doth not admit a
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15197:30"/> perpetuall vacuity. <hi>Ionathan</hi> cannot excuſe vs at the great feaſt day, when our good King calleth for vs.</p>
            <p>Soone after the Creation, men liued longer, that the earth might be peopled: Now towards the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation, they dye the ſooner, that the heauens may be with greater ſpeede repleniſhed: Doe wee not ſee that a Father will ſometimes part with his owne ſonne, to be his friends by adoption? will not one kinde neighbour pull vp his tender plants, to pleaſure, and ſupply the vaſte ground of another? and ſhall <hi>Eden</hi> lye waſte, the garden of our God? ſhall he want ſonnes when wee haue any that can content him? or plants to repleniſh it?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> What ſhall I more ſay? Is not euery faithfull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon a pillar or poſte in that heauenly houſe that is aboue? muſt they not then, by death, be cut downe out of the thicke forreſt of this world? hewne forth of the craggy Rocke here below? and be carried and conuered from hence to heauen? otherwiſe, how ſhould the Lords building, and Chriſts miſticall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy be perfected? When the materiall Temple was a making, was not matter fetcht from farre? And ſhall not the great <hi>Salomon</hi> aboue, gather his ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſtones and fetch his choifeſt timber from the foure ends of the world? Hee that is about to build, will hee not cut downe the moſt ancient Oke or Elmo? what if they would keepe off the beames of the ſcorching Sunne? ſhelter thee vnder their coole and (much to be deſired) ſhade? beate backe the bluſtring and bitter ſhowres, &amp; ſtormes? Yet, downe they muſt, notwithſtanding their
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15197:31"/> profit, pleaſure, or (the which man naturally af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects) antiquity: otherwiſe how ſhould the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding begun be perfected, well edified? Gods plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant plants (we grant) on earth, by their preſence and prayers, would yeelde the Church much comfort, benefit; but then the new Ieruſalem would not at all be made perfect. Mourne not therefore ouer-much, for thy friends departed; for this were to grieue ouer-much, that Gods building goeth too faſt forward.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> And in concluſion; yet ſomething more may be added to take away immoderate paſſion. Be not thy friends Trauellers, ſea-faring men? are they not arriued and landed ſafe at the hauen of heauen? Neuer did poore Mariner (after hee had beene long abſent in a ſtrange land, in danger of ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke, amidſt the terribleſt ſtorme, purſued night and day by the cruell Pyrates) reioyce more to ſtep off the hatches, to ſhore, at his owne home; then the faithfull ſoule, hauing beene toſſed in this world, is, to depart from the body, to take poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the higheſt heauens, it's naturall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</p>
            <p>And what can I more ſay? Are not wee our ſelues come to the very brinke of lorden? muſt wee not one day (and that before long) land at the Key of Canaan? And ſhall not they and we then, for euer in glory and peace remaine toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</p>
            <p>Ponder this ſeriouſly, beleeue it vnfainedly, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it particularly; and then, for thy friends de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture (if thou canſt) mourne immoderately.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15197:31"/>
            <p>NOw hauing ſpoke of the Text, what I purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; I perſwade my ſelfe, it will be expected that I ſhould ſay ſomething in the praiſe of her, whoſe Funerals, at this preſent be celebrated; the which I am vnwilling, yet willing to doe: vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, becauſe it hath not beene my vſuall cuſtome vpon the like occaſion; and therefore I may giue offence to ſome in the Congregation: Againe, it is to be feared, that ſome Preachers imitate bad Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers (let this be no preiudice to the beſt,) who for a fee, will pleade and commend any cauſe, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king good of euill, and euill of good; making the heauens to lowre, grow darke, and ſhrowd themſelues in a vaile of blackeneſſe; more like to weedes of mourning, then the perſons, attired with their ſuites of ſorrow, in the preſent aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly.</p>
            <p>Yet I am willing to ſay ſomewhat; firſt, becauſe I know for whom I am to ſpeake, it's either God, or his ſeruant departed. God (I aſſure my ſelfe) as he would haue the name <hi>of the wicked to rot;</hi> ſo would he, that <hi>The memoriall of the righteous ſhould remaine for euer:</hi> And, a true teſtimony is a good action, vnto which he hath (though not by way of merit) annexed a reward: why then ſhould I in this thing be ſilent, if my heart be vpright?</p>
            <p>Now for the perſon departed, I know in part with whom I haue to deale; and all that I will ſay, is either what I haue heard by the report of credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſons, or haue knowne by my owne experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which is, either concerning her publique
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:15197:32"/> carriage, or priuate conuerſation: of both the which I haue not much (though much might be ſaid) to vtter.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 paragraph">
                     <desc>〈1 paragraph〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>She, in reſpect of her birth and pedigree, ſhall of me receiue no praiſe (though, for any thing I know, in that commendable:) we are all of one blood; God little reſpects to commend that in any: and they are moſt honourably (as I perſwade my ſelfe ſhe was) deſcended, that are borne againe by the word and ſpirit; and where the Lord is ſilent, I wiſh to be ſilent alſo.</p>
            <p>For her publique carriage, I haue heard that, which if I ſhould at large relate, would much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to her commendation; but it is ſo well, to the moſt here preſent, knowne; that I omit all, ſaue one thing; which is, that ſhe was a Notary, and tooke the Sermons which ſhe heard, by her owne penne. I know not what ſome will iudge of this action, but I hope the beſt cannot but giue it a Chriſtian probation: ſhee did this, when as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny (by much meaner then ſhee) come with their Fannes and Feathers; whereas (mee ſeemes) a Gooſe-quill would farre better befit their fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</p>
            <p>But a priuate life is leaſt ſubiect to hypocriſie; therefore I proceede to that. I haue beene credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly informed, that ſhee did in her Chamber re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peate to her Maid-ſeruants, the Sermons ſhee had heard and penned; Catechiſe them in the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Religion; and, vpon euery fit occaſion, would labour to ſeaſon them with the true feare of the Lord. Againe, ſhe ſpent (hauing health) three
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15197:32"/> or foure houres in her priuate Cloſet euery day, in Reading, Meditating, Praying, and Writing. But what was the ſubiect? for otherwiſe to write is no great commendation: Amongſt other things (all tending to good vſes) ſhe hath left (and that in no ſmall volume) diuers diſputations, that ſhee had with Separatiſts and Papiſts; her anſweres; and what was her owne reſolution in the controuerted opinions; annexing her reaſons. Moreouer, (as one that expected the time of her change before it came) ſhe left vnder her owne hand, what (if it might ſtand with her huſbands good pleaſure) ſhe would haue performed; as diuers gifts to ſeuerall perſons, both for cloath and coyne, in value a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounting to a large ſumme; And her deſire was, that there might be no blacks worne for her, at her Funerals, except by her owne houſe at the moſt, or in particular, by her deare and eſpeciall friend; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe had rather haue them receiue ſome pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate gifts of remembrance; and, in that ſhe would not follow the common cuſtome of the world: It was not couetouſneſſe, (I perſwade my ſelfe) but conſcience, that fruſtrated, in that reſpect, any mans expectation.</p>
            <p>And thus hauing touched a few particulars; I come in briefe to mention, what my ſelfe can ſpeak by experience: And that is, either in the time of her health, or ſickeneſſe: In which former conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I not many times came into her preſence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the diſtance of our habitations: But for her apparell, it was ſo modeſt, not <hi>with gold put about, or broidered haire,</hi> that a curious eye could
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15197:33"/> not iuſtly picke a quarrell at it: her ſpeech was not much; her words well compoſed, and the matter ſuch, as to a iudicious Auditor might yeeld com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and in ſome thing adminiſter profitable edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <p>In the time of her ſickeneſſe, I heard her neuer vtter one word, that fauoured of impatience: ſhee tooke all helpes willingly, that might haue reſtored her (if God had giuen the bleſſing) to health and her former condition: and in the receipt, ſhe would pray, and deſire others alſo, that God would <hi>bleſſe it to her.</hi> And ſhe ſpake much in the commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Goſpell; affirming, that all things, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that, were worth nothing. She left certaine Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles to be deliuered to her daughters, with this writ on them; <hi>I haue ſaid, that my fleſh ſhall periſh and rot: But the word of the Lord ſhall endure for euer: And bleſſed ſhall you be, if you conſtantly, vnto the end, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to ſeeke and follow that, with faithfull and true hearts.</hi> She alſo gaue a gift to the Paſtor of that place, by which, ſhe ſaid, ſhe would tye him, to be as carefull ouer the pooreſt ſheepe in his flocke, as if he were the greateſt Lord. Not long before her death, ſhe ſaid, that ſhe hoped God would giue her power againſt the Enemie: (But alas! we many of vs, cannot tell, what by Enemie, is meant,) which phraſe of hers, ſtroke into me a deepe ſuſpition, that her change was neere at hand: For I haue alwayes obſerued, that when Sathan moſt tempteth the truely-religious, they ſeldome recouer of that ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: He hath great skill to diſcerne how Nature
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:15197:33"/> is weakened; and therefore taketh the fitteſt time for his purpoſe.</p>
            <p>She prayed with iudgement and affection, not long before her deſolution. In the which petitions, ſhe vſed words and ſentences, worthy of admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, imitation. She mentioned the King in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar; remembred his kingdomes and ſubiects, with others, (that for breuity I paſſe ouer) as her friends, kinsfolkes, and children.</p>
            <p>Theſe things I my ſelfe ſaw and heard, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, that were worthy to be recorded, and of the beſt practiſed. At which time I abſented my ſelfe out of the chamber; neither after that, heard I her voyce, or ſaw her face; for within a ſhort ſpace ſhe departed.</p>
            <p>From all which I wiſh we may (for, I am ſure, we ought to) learne inſtruction.</p>
            <closer>Laus Deo.</closer>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
